Guide to the J. Martin Evans Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
J. Martin Evans papers
1943-2011
SC1163
Evans, J. Martin (John Martin), 1935-2013.
15 Linear feet and 216 megabytes
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
John Martin Evans was born in Cardiff, Wales, on Feb. 2, 1935. After a two-year stint working in military intelligence for the Royal Air Force from 1953 to 1955, Evans attended Oxford, where he received his BA in 1958 from Jesus College, and his MA and DPhil from Merton College in 1963. At Oxford, his thesis advisor was Dame Helen Gardner, the doyenne of 17th-century studies. Under her guidance, he began a lifelong career in Milton studies. Gardner was influential in other ways: She convinced Evans to apply to Stanford when the academic job market in Britain was so poor that 250 scholars with doctorates in English were competing for two university positions.
Evans was offered the job, and immediately flew to Switzerland and proposed to Mariella Lafranchi, whom he had met at Oxford. He didn't know half her family had emigrated to California decades before; Evans moved into a large extended family in the United States and never looked back.
In 2004, the Milton Society of America named him as a prestigious "honored scholar" for lifetime achievement.
He hosted a 400th birthday party for John Milton in 2008, with a marathon reading of Paradise Lost – some called it a "Martinfest." The event reunited many of his former students from across the United States and Canada.
At his death, he was in his 50th year of teaching at Stanford. He held many awards for his teaching and service, including the Bing Award for teaching (1992), the Richard W. Lyman Award (1990) and the Dean's Award for Distinguished Teaching (1984). The 1987 Walter J. Gores Award for Excellence in Teaching cited "the magnificence of his teaching at all levels of the department curriculum" and "the passion about literature that infuses all his teaching and writing."
Evans was associate dean of the School of Humanities and Sciences (1977-81), director of undergraduate studies (1983-86) and chair of the English Department (1988-91). He was named the William R. Kenan Jr. Professor in 2002.
He was a champion of the humanities, and passionate in their defense: "The humanist's material is not a mysterious concatenation of natural phenomena or a mass of raw statistical data waiting to be given significance by the ordering mind of the analyst," he wrote in a 2009 article in Stanford magazine.
Evans was survived by his wife of almost 50 years, Mariella Evans of Stanford; his daughter Jessica Evans, his son-in-law Yung Duong and grandson, Owen Evans-Duong, all of Oakland; and his daughter Joanna Evans and son-in-law David Harris of Ojai, Calif.
Cynthia Haven http://news.stanford.edu/news/2013/february/martin-evans-obit-021513.html
Access Terms
Milton, John; English literature--Study and teaching.; Stanford University--Faculty.; Universities and colleges--Faculty.
Collection Contents
- Publications
  - Evans, Martin, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poetic Agency - Byron (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Augustine (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poetic Agency - WW (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Introduction: Week 9 English 5 Lit-Politics - Quiet American (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Introduction: Week 8 English 5 Lit-History: Brecht (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Montaigne (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Montaigne (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brecht's Galileo (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Green's The Quiet American (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Poetic Ageing (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Textual Selves: Intro (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Augustine / Dante (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Poetic Agency - Byron (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Biblio (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Published Articles - COMUS & No (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - SEC Sources (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Misc. Notes and Papers (1 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Misc. Notes and Papers (2 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Misc. Notes and Papers (3 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Augustine and Dante (Draft) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Reciprocal Vision (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - A Humanities Forum, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bacchus, Books, and Bards, 2010 Jan (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - America: The Open Society, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1999 Sep/1999 Oct (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - London - Corridors of Power, Contains draft, "Corridors of Power: The British Political System" (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Paris - Americans in Paris, Contains draft, "Americans in Paris". (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Job Applications 1979 O-T, Contains "Keeping Faith with Desire" and "The politics of androgyny" by Barbara Charlesworth Gelpi; "Narcissus Interrupted: Specularity and the Subject of the Tudor State" and "Protestant Erotics: Idolatry and Interpretation in Spenser's Faerie Queene" by Linda Gregerson; publication, "The Worlds of Victorian Fiction"; "My Grande Naufrage: Fiction and Political Obsession", "Was Lia de Putti dead at 22?", "Notes on the rhetoric of anti-realist fiction", and "The Illuminating Distortion" by Albert J. Guerard. (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Job Applications 1979 U-Z, Contains several publications by John Felstiner: "The Biography of a Poem" (on Paul Celan); "Translating Paul Celan's Du sei wie du"; "Paul Celan: The Strain of Jewishness"; "Repetition and Restitution: Translating Celan's Die Winzer"; "The Natural Prayer of the Soul"; and "Changing Faces in Max Beerbohm's Caricature". "Kafka and the Golem - Translating Paul Celan"; "The Island Worlds of Darwin and Melville" by H. Bruce Franklin; "Your Humble Servant: Strategic Humility in Bradstreet, Dickinson, and Jonson" by Kenneth Fields; issues from New Literary History, Religion and Literature, and Representations. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Brooks, Helen Mae B., Contains publications by Terry Castle: "Eros and Liberty at the English Masquerade, 1710-90"; "Contagious Folly: An Adventure and its Skeptics"; "Sex Please--We're British"; "High Plains Drifter" (on Don Quixote). Publications by William A. Clebsch: "The Elizabethans on Luther"; "Southern Religion Resurrected"; "America's 'Mythique' as Redeemer Nation". Publications by W.B. Carnochan: "Darkly wise, rudely great"; "Where did great books come from anyway?"; "The Case of Julius Goebel". Other miscellaneous articles and publications from scholarly journals. (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Boyer, Helen Anne, Contains "Timelessness, Foreknowledge, and Free Will" by Dennis Danielson; "Dante and the Verace Intendimento of the Nature Introduction"; "Alexandrian Methods of Interpretation and the Rabbis" by David Daube; "A Reading of the Changeling" and "Nebuchadnezzar's Children: Conventions of Madness in Middle English Literature" by Penelope B.R. Doob. (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Campbell, Rolla Bruce D. (Box 8, Folder 30)
    Contains publications by Robert W. Ackerman: "Sir Gawain and the Green Knight and its Intepreters"; "Sir Frederic Madden and the Study of Medieval Literature"; "Review: The Book of Kyng Arthur: The Unity of Malory's Morte Darther"; "Malory's Ironsyde". Publications by Alfred Appel, Jr.: "An Interview with Vladimir Nabokov"; "Vladimir Nabokov"; "Powerhouse's Blues"; "Lolita: The Springboard of Parody"; January 1967 issues of The New Republic; other publications on Beowulf and Dante.
  - Job Applications 1980 A-G (Box 8, Folder 31)
    Contains several publications by Herbert Lindenberger and others.
  - Borchers, Donald Gay (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Contains "Poetry and Equity: Aristotle's Defense of Fiction" by Kathy Eden; "Agamemnon's Decision: Freedom and Folly in Aeschylus" by Mark W. Edwards; "A Muse of Fire: Henry V in the Light of Tamburlaine" by Robert Egan.
  - Brown, Rodney W. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Contains "Epicurus and Voluptas in Late Antiquity: The Curious Testimony of Martianus Capella", "The Poet's Last Words: Text and Meaning at the End of the Parson's Prologue", Chaucer, the Merchant, and their Tale: Getting Beyond Old Controversies", and "Proserpina, Matelda, and the Pilgrim" by Emerson Brown, Jr.; "Love and Marriage in the Age of Chaucer" by Henry Ansgar Kelly; "Bede the Educator" by George Hardin Brown; chapter, "A New History of the Enlightenment?" from "The Profession of Eighteenth-Century Literature" by John Bender; chapter, "Prison Reform and the Sentence of Narration in The Vicar of Wakefield" from "The New Eighteenth Century" by John Bender; "The Day of the Tempest" and "Liberating the Sister Arts: The Revolution of Blake's Infant Sorrow" by John Bender; "Of Mice and Women: Thoughts on Chaucerian Allusion"; several publications from scholarly journals.
  - Job Applications 1979 A-G (Box 8, Folder 25)
    Contains chapter, "Areopagitica and Liberty" by Blair Hoxby from The Oxford Handbook of Milton; "Maiden in the Mor Lay and the medieval Magdalene Tradition" by Joseph Harris; "The Myden Makeles" by David G. Halliburton; publications from the Journal of English and Germanic Philology; Deutsches Dante-Jahrbuch, American Academy of Religion, A Journal of Medieval Studies, and Renaissance Quarterly.
  - Job Applications 1980 H-N (Box 8, Folder 33)
    Contains "Shakespeare's Sonnets: Age in Love and the Goring of Thoughts" by John Klause (from Studies in Philology, 1983); "Religious Language in Waiting for Godot" by V.A. Kolve (from The Centennial Review, 1967); "Political Theory and the Uses of the Self" by Nannerl O. Keohane (from Journal of Politics, 1975).
  - Job Applications 1980 O-T (Box 8A, Folder 34)
    Contains October 1998 issue of "Speculum: A Journal of Medieval Studies".
  - Job Applications 1980 U-Z (Box 8A, Folder 35)
    Contains "The Blind" by Arturo Islas (from a Spring 1986 issue of "Zyzzyva").
  - Tolan, John Justin, 1997-2002 (Box 8A, Folder 36)
    Contains "Virginia Woolf and the Arts: Selected Papers from the Sixth Annual Conference on Virginia Woolf"; review by Terry Castle on "Casanova: The Man who Really Loved Women" by Lydia Flem and "History of my Life" by Giacomo Casanova (from The New Republic); "Either Or or And" by Nicholas Jenkins (from Yale Review); "The Monster in the Rainbows: Keats and the Science of Life" by Denise Gigante (from The Modern Language Association of America); "Textual Icons: Reading Early Modern Illustrations" by Stephen Orgel (from The Renaissance Computer); "Professions and Conversations on the Future of Literary and Cultural Studies" by Donald E. Hall; "Chicana Feminism and Postmodernist Theory" by Paula M.L. Moya (from Journal of Women in Culture and Society); "Literature and the Other Arts" by Herbert Lindenberger (from The Cambridge History of Literary Criticism).
  - Watts, Craig, 2001-2003 (Box 8A, Folder 38)
    Contains miscellaneous student files; graduate school application and student essays.
  - Varela-Sanchez, Manuel (Box 8A, Folder 37)
    Contains 2000 issue of the Milton Quarterly; "Monuments and Ruins: Spenser and the Problem of the English Library" by Jennifer Summit; "Keeping up with the Past" by George Dekker; "Everybody Hates Kant: Blakean Formalism and the Symmetries of Laura Moriarty" by Robert Kaufman; "Tobacco and Boys: How Queer was Marlowe?" by Stephen Orgel; "Negatively Capable Dialectics: Keats, Vendler, Adorno, and the Theory of the Avant-Garde" by Robert Kaufman; "Milton's Aesthetics of Eating" by Denise Gigante; "Topography as Historiography: Petrarch, Chaucer, and the Making of Medieval Rome" by Jennifer Summit; "The Case for Comus" by Stephen Orgel; "The Favorite Child: David Copperfield and the Scriptural Issue of Child-Wives" by Robert M. Polhemus; "Latin Annotations in a Copy of Stowe's Chaucer and the Seventeenth-Century Reception of Troilus and Criseyde".
  - Vincent, Lawrence Marc, 1965-1993 (Box 8A, Folder 39)
    Contains several publications by Mary F. Wack: "New Medieval Medical Texts on amor hereos"; "The Liber de heros morbo of Johannes Afflacius and its Implications for Medieval Love Conventions"; "Imagination, Medicine, and Rhetoric in Andreas Capellanus' De Amore"; "Wolfram's Dawn Song, Sine Klawen"; "Lovesickness in Troilus"; miscellaneous publications by other scholars.
  - Wangenheim, Adam M., 1997 (Box 8A, Folder 40)
    Contains 1997 issue of the Official Journal of the International Society for the History of Medicine.
  - West, Wendy, 1968-2005 (Box 8A, Folder 41)
    Contains several publications by Wesley Trimpi: "Whose Worth's Unknown, although his Height be Taken"; "Reason and the Classical Premises of Literary Decorum"; "Konrad Gessner and Neoplatonic Poets"; "The Practice of Historical Interpretation and Nashe's Brightnesse Falls from the Ayre"; "Ben Jonson his Best Piece of Poetrie"; publication from a 1989 issue of The Cambridge History of Literary Criticism; "Sir Philip Sidney's An apology for poetry"; miscellaneous publications by other scholars.
  - Wilson, Craig David, 1943-1983 (Box 8A, Folder 42)
    Contains several publications by Jim Swan: "Giving New Depth to the Surface: Psychoanalysis, Literature, and Society"; application for faculty research fellowship; "Betwixt Two Labyrinths: Andrew Marvell's Rational Amphibian"; "Mater and Nannie: Freud's Two Mothers and the Discovery of the Oedipus Complex"; "History, Pastoral and Desire: Andrew Marvell's Mower Poems". Publications by G.F. Sensabaugh: "English Studies and the Crisis in Education"; "Tragic Effect in Webster's The White Devil"; two reviews from Renaissance Quarterly; miscellaneous publications from other scholars.
  - Zattiero, Glenn, 1972-1994 (Box 8A, Folder 43)
    Contains several publications by Robert M. Polhemus: "Being in Love with Phineas Finn/Phineas Redux: Desire, Devotion, Consolation"; review on "Anthony Trollope and his Contemporaries: A Study in the Theory and Conventions of Mid-Victorian Fiction" by David Skilton and "South Africa" by Anthony Trollope; "Lewis Carroll and the Child in Victorian Fiction"; "John Millais's Children: Faith, Erotics, and The Woodman's Daughter"; publications by Nancy Huddleston Packer: "The Women Who Walk"; "Second Wind"; "Homecoming"; "Cousins"; "The Day the Tree Fell Down"; miscellaneous publications by other scholars.
  - Marjorie Perloff Publications (Box 8A, Folder 44)
    Contains "What to make of a Dimished Thing"; "Crisis in the Humanities?"; "On Wanting to be a Comparatist".
  - Hevel, Claudia Ann, 1984-2003 (Box 8A, Folder 46)
    Contains publications by Stephen Orgel: "The Example of Hercules"; "Shakespeare in stunning full colour"; offprint from "England and the Continental Renaissance"; "Insolent women and manlike apparel"; "Original copies".
  - Zulevic, Daniel Tynan, 1965 (Box 8A, Folder 45)
    Contains "The Quest of Seth, Solomon's Ship and the Grail" by Esther Casier Quinn.
  - Hill, George Richard, 1990 (Box 8A, Folder 47)
    Contains script of retreat talk from October 1990.
  - Honegger, Barbara Suzanne, 1967-1994 (Box 8A, Folder 48)
    Contains publications by Thomas C. Moser: "Ford Maddox Hueffer and Under Western Eyes"; book reviews; "Joseph Conrad: Achievement and Decline". Publications by Anne K. Mellor: "Keats's Face of Moneta: Source and Meaning"; "Blake's Designs for The Book of Thel: An Affirmation of Innocence"; "The Human Form Divine and the Structure of Blake's Jerusalem"; book reviews.
  - Yoerg, Sharon Kay P, 1975-1993 (Box 8A, Folder 49)
    Contains a collection of publications on Medieval and Renaissance literature and other topics.
  - Publications by A.G. Rigg and F.C. Robinson, 1964-1978 (Box 8A, Folder 50)
    Contains publications by A.G. Rigg: "Hoccleve's Complaint and Isidore of Seville"; "The Letter C and the Date of Easter"; book review. Publications by F.C. Robinson: "Names in Old English Literature"; "The Complaynt Off Sanct Cipraine, The Grett Nigromancer: A Poem by Anthony Ascham"; "Review: Beowulf and the Fight at Finnsburgh: A Bibliography (D.K. Fry)"; "Beowulf's Retreat from Frisia: Some Textual Problems"; "Two Non-Cruces in Beowulf"; "Review: Old English Poetry: Fifteen Essays (R.P. Creed, Ed.)"; "Verb Tense in Blake's The Tyger"; "Lexicography and Literary Criticism: A Caveat". February 1970 and September 1971 copies of the Old English Newsletter; a June 1964 copy of The Oxford Magazine.
  - Publications by Lucio Ruotolo and Lawrence V. Ryan, 1964-1982 (Box 8A, Folder 51)
    Contains publications by Lucio Ruotolo: "Keats and Kierksgaard: The Tragedy of Two Worlds"; "Mrs. Dalloway: The journey out of subjectivity"; "Three Prelude Events: The Growth of a Poet's Faith"; "Brighton Rock's Absurd Heroine"; "The Trinitarian Framework of Donne's Holy Sonnet XIV"; "Mrs. Dalloway: The Unguarded Moment". Publications by Lawrence V. Ryan: "Opening Address"; "Richard Hakluyt's Voyage Into Aristotle"; "The Shorter Latin Poem in Tudor England"; "Three Sonnets on Roman Life by Trilussa" (translations); "Conrad Celtis and the Mystique of Number"; "Erasmi Convivia: The Banquet Colloquies of Erasmus"; "The Canon's Yeoman's Desperate Confession"; "Stornei, Gru, Colombe: The Bird Images in Inferno V"; "Art and Artifice in Erasmus' Convivium Profanum".
  - Misc. Notes and Papers (4 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Textual Selves
    - Textual Selves (1 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Contains "Introduction"; "The Divided Self: Augustine's Confessions" (2 copies); "The Immutable Self: Thomas Hardy's The Mayor of Casterbridge"; and "Fantasy-Land"
    - Textual Selves (2 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Contains "The First-Person Epic: Dante's Divine Comedy"; "The Multiple Self: The Essays of Michael de Montaigne"; "Authorial Agency: Milton's Poetic Self-Construction; and "The Egotistical Sublime: Wordsworth's Resolution and Independence and Byron's Childe Harold's Pilgrimage"
    - Textual Selves (3 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Contains "Selves and Others: Twain's Innocents Abroad and James's The American Scene"; "The Fictional I: Graham Greene's Quiet American"; "Confession: Graham Greene's Quiet American"; and "Acknowledgements"
    - Textual Selves (4 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Contains "Wide Open Spaces"; "Departed Glories: American Writers in Italy"; "Native Sons: European Views of American Men"; and "Mother Land: American Writers in England"
    - Textual Selves - Intro (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Textual Selves: Identity in Literature (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Contains Introduction and Chapters 1-3: "The Divided Self"; "The Multiple Self"; and "Poetic Agency"
    - Textual Selves: Identity in Literature (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Contains Chapters 4-7: "The Egotistical Sublime"; "Alien Encounters"; "The Immutable Self"; "The Fictional 'I'"; and Bibliography
    - Textual Selves Copy 2 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains Introduction and Chapters 1-4: "The Divided Self - Augustine and Dante"; "The Multiple Self - Montaigne"; "Poetic Agency - Milton"; and "The Egotistical Sublime - Wordsworth and Byron"
    - Textual Selves Copy 2 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Contains Chapters 5-9: "Alien Encounters - Twain and James"; "The Immutable Self - Hardy"; "The Fictional 'I' - Greene"; "The Drama of Stasis - T.S. Eliot"; "The Hero with Two Faces - Brecht"; and Bibliography
  - Misc. Poems (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Contains copies of poems in Williams’ anthology; Sonnet 116; "They Flee from Me" by Sir Thomas Wyatt; "Nature, that Washed her Hands in Milk" by Sir Walter Raleigh.
  - Misc. Files and Notes (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Contains hand-written notes; partially complete draft on America as the New World; 1964 article from The Illustrated London News, "Pamela. The Earliest English Novel"; 2007 article from TIME, "Inventing America: The 400th Anniversary of Jamestown".
  - Triumphs: Two Chamber Plays (Box 8, Folder 32)
    Contains pressboard binder with two plays inside: "Miss Cramm" and "Odysseus and the Cyclops"; appendices contain music notes, including fragments of ancient Greek music arranged for recorder by Donald C. Johns.
  - The Theoretical Posture (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Unfortunate Traveller - Thomas Nashe (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Contains excerpts from "The Unfortunate Traveller" by Thomas Nashe.
  - Sargent's Italy, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Contains student essay, "Sargent's Italy" from MLA 93, "Italy in the Anglo-American Imagination".
  - Stories
    - Stories (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Contains printouts of excerpts from "A Month by the Lake" by H.E. Bates; "Pictures of Fidelman" by Bernard Malamud; "Cuttlefish Bones" by Eugenio Montale; and "Twilight in Italy" by D.H. Lawrence.
    - Stories (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Contains printouts from "The Carburetor"; "Made in USSR"; "The Story of a Panic"; "Don Juan" by Lord Byron; poems by G.K. Chesterton; "The Three Fat Women of Antibes"; "Chagrin in Three Parts"; "America the Menace"; "Extra Virgin" by Annie Hawes; "Mario and the Magician" by Thomas Mann; the ninth day/third story from "The Decameron" by Giovanni Boccaccio; and "The Innocents Abroad" by Mark Twain. Also contains hand-written notes.
    - Cruise 2005 Stories (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Contains printouts from "Letters from my Windmill"; "Roman Fever" by Edith Wharton; "The Leopard" by Giuseppe di Lampedusa; and poems by Lord Byron.
    - Bedtime Stories (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Contains printouts of excerpts from "Voices of Gallipoli" by Maurice Shadbolt; "The Mill on the Po" by Riccardo Bacchelli; "Rappaccini's Daughter" by Nathaniel Hawthorne; "Ferrara and my Last Duchess" by Louis S. Friedland; "Teem - A Treasure-Hunter" by Rudyard Kipling; "On the Extinction of the Venetian Republic" by William Wordsworth; poems by Lord Byron; and "Ithaka" by Constantine Cavafy. Also contains hand-written notes.
    - Bedtime Stories (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Contains printouts from "Ithaka" by Constantine Cavafy; "Italian Neighbors" by Tim Parks; "The Wilder Shores of Love" by Aimee Dubucq de Rivery; "Teem - A Treasure Hunter"; "The Fall of the Byzantine Empire"; "Where Angels Fear to Tread" by E.M. Forster; a preface by Iris Origo; "The Story of San Michele"; "Hero and Leander" by Christopher Marlowe; poems by W.B. Yeats; "Etruscan Places" by D.H. Lawrence; "Sea and Sardinia" by D.H. Lawrence; "Roman Fever" by Edith Wharton; "Albergo Empedocle" by E.M. Forster; "The Leopard" by Giuseppe di Lampedusa; and "The Story of a Panic".
- Teaching
  - Lectures
    - The Paradise of Exiles (1 of 2), 2003-2004; Script and supplemental materials from a presentation on Lord Byron (delivered at a hotel overlooking the gulf of La Spezia) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - The Paradise of Exiles (2 of 2), Contains draft of script, "The Paradise of Exiles" (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sea of Dreams, Contains draft of script, "The Land of Dreams" from a talk on the French Riviera (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Towards Abstraction, Contains draft of script, "Towards Abstraction: The Interior World of Henry Matisse"; news article from the San Francisco Chronicle on "The Unknown Matisse" by Hilary Spurling; hand-written notes. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lectures - Athens - Rome, 2003; Contains drafts of scripts: "Greece in the Western Imagination"; "The Knights of Saint John" (plus chronology); "The Salvation of Christendom: The Battle of Lepanto"; supplemental news article and passages. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Palio (+ Siena Sieve), Contains magazine clippings; handwritten notes; draft on the "Siena Sieve" portrait. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Biblio, Empty file (Box 3, Folder 37)